PINAKI DUTTA

Pune, Maharashtra • (864) 302-0766 • pinakidutta.1@gmail.com • linkedin.com/in/pinakid/

PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

Dedicated IT Financial Data Analyst with over 11.8 years of experience in PMO, Finance, Data, and Technology Business Management (TBM). Collaborated with cross-functional teams across the organization, including key stakeholders and customers, to define project scope, resource requirements, budget, timeline, deliverables, and milestones.

EDUCATION

UNIVERSITY AT BUFFALO, THE STATE UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK

Master of Business Administration, Management Science, STEM

Jun. 2023

Concentration: Finance & Analytics, GPA: 3.789/4.00

 Relevant Courses - Business Strategy, Financial Accounting for Managers, Accounting for Decision-Making, Financial Analysis for Managers, IT for Managers, Investment Management, International Finance Management, M&A Strategy, Financial Modeling, Fixed Income Securities, Multinational Banking, Data Modeling, Database Management System

SRM INSTITUTE OF SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY, CHENNAI, INDIA

Bachelor of Technology, Civil Engineering

May 2011

GPA: 3.76/4.00 (US Equivalent), Graduated First Class with Distinction

EXPERIENCE

Finance Intern, JADE GLOBAL, INC., Buffalo, NY, USA

July 2022-Aug. 2022

- Collected and reviewed articles for literature review and learned order booking to collection cycle in IT service industry
- Interviewed industry leaders and CXOs of various companies to understand their IT outsourcing challenges
- Presented findings on changing landscape of IT service industry to a panel of experts, senior executives, and CFO

Data Team Lead, TATA CONSULTANCY SERVICES LIMITED, Edison, NJ, USA

May 2018-Aug. 2021

- Collaborated with customer to transform business data requirements for IT Cost Transparency module in TBMS
- Acted as liaison between IT and Corporate Finance to address analytics queries and remove financial roadblocks
- · Maintained efficiency in RFP process by having a thorough understanding of all departmental information
- Coordinated with customers to review monthly billing worth \$6M+ and processed those invoices in SAP Fieldglass
- Prioritized team activities to achieve and maintain a highly productive workforce in a deadline-driven environment

Data Analyst, TATA CONSULTANCY SERVICES LIMITED, Chennai, India

Aug. 2016-Apr. 2018

- Streamlined data processing and established data transparency to provide team and data users with accessibility, consistency, and a transparent overview of 100+ data sets by creating Standard Operating Procedures (SOPs)
- Utilized APIs and custom functions in Apptio to streamline the month-end close process for the Bill of IT, resulting in a 40% reduction in processing time, from 5 weeks to 3 weeks
- Audited journal entries before being posted into SAP General ledger and reconciled 5+ IT accounts for corporate finance

IT Financial Analyst, TATA CONSULTANCY SERVICES LIMITED, Chennai, India

Sep. 2011-Jul. 2016

- Managed IT Project Management Operations (PMO) with projects worth \$5M+ and 400+ FTEs
- Coordinated with Business Relationship Managers in project planning activities, monitored and tracked actual revenue numbers, identified risks, and devised a mitigation plan to handle variance with budgeted amount
- Assessed billing leakage trend and executed a plan to reduce it, resulting in a 2% increase in profitability every quarter

SKILLS

- IT Skills: Advanced Excel Data modeling (VLOOKUP, Index-Match, Nested Ifs, Sum Product, Pivot Tables, Conditional Formatting, Data Tables), Microsoft Office suites (Excel, Outlook, PowerPoint, and Word), Apptio, Jira, SAP Fieldglass
- Finance Skills: Financial Statement Analysis (Revenue, COGS, Gross Profit, SG&A, EBITDA and capital expenditures trend analysis), Discounted Cash Flow (DCF) Valuation, Price-Volume Analysis, Hedging strategies (futures, options, and swaps) to minimize currency risks in international trade, Efficient Frontier Technique, Macro-economic analysis
- Project Management Skills: Create group charter, Create Work Breakdown Structure (WBS), Develop Gantt Chart

CERTIFICATIONS

Bloomberg Market Concepts (BMC), DP-900: Azure Data Fundamentals, APPTIO Elite TBMA, AINS 21